Inventory of the R. Freeman Butts papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Education Commission of the States clippings, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 278: 3-4)
- Correspondence with James M. Banner, Jr., 1986 (Box-folder 278: 5)
- National Commission on Secondary Vocational Education clippings, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 278: 6)
- Smithsonian symposium on George Orwell correspondence and clippings, 1983 (Box-folder 278: 7)
- National Commission on the Role and Future of State Colleges and Universities clippings, 1986 (Box-folder 278: 8)
- Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development correspondence, newsletters, and reports, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 278: 9)
- Committee for Economic Development clippings, 1985 (Box-folder 278: 10)
- Research materials, 1981-1989
  - Corporate role in education, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 278: 11)
  - Student test scores, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 278: 12)
  - Magnet schools, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 278: 13)
  - Schools near workplaces, 1983 (Box-folder 278: 14)
  - Teachers unions, 1983-1989 (Box-folder 278: 15)
  - Educational technology, 1983 (Box-folder 278: 16)
  - Social studies, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 279: 1)
- California Bicentennial Commission correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 279: 2)
- California History-Social Science Framework correspondence and drafts, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 279: 3-4)
- California model curriculum standards and correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 279: 5)
- Papers on the history of social studies, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 279: 6)
- National Council for the Social Studies correspondence and clippings, 1985 (Box-folder 279: 7)
- Correspondence with Alan L. Lockwood, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 279: 8)
- Project SPAN (Social Studies/Social Science Education: Priorities, Practices, and Needs) correspondence and reports, 1980
- Papers on radical pedagogy, 1979-1989 (Box-folder 280: 2-3)
- Papers on compulsory education, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 280: 4)
- Background material on the Family Choice Initiative, 1979 (Box-folder 280: 5)
- Foundation for Teaching Economics correspondence and conference papers, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 281: 1-3)
- Paul Gagnon correspondence and writings, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 281: 4-5)
- Paula O'Connnor correspondence and paper, 1989 (Box-folder 281: 6)
- National Council for the Social Studies articles and newsletter, 1979-1989 (Box-folder 282: 1-2)
- "A Personal Appreciation of Hazel Whitman Hertzberg", 1988 (Box-folder 282: 3)
- Hazel Hertzberg correspondence and papers, 1970-1988 (Box-folder 282: 4-5)
- General correspondence, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 282: 6)
- Recommendations for Richard C. Remy, 1989 (Box-folder 282: 7)
- Correspondence, 1978-1990 (Box-folder 282: 8)
  - Pete McCloskey, 1978 (Box-folder 282: 9)
  - Charles Lyons and Ron Galbraith, 1978-1988 (Box-folder 282: 10)
  - Jim Banner, 1988 (Box-folder 282: 11)
  - Ron Goodenow and Henry Bolter, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 282: 12)
  - Claude Eggertsen, 1985 (Box-folder 282: 13)
  - Gene Schwilck, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 282: 14)
- Kettering Foundation correspondence, minutes, and proposals, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 283: 1-11)
- Truman Pierce Institute correspondence and announcement, 1984 (Box-folder 283: 12)
- Pew Charitable Trusts correspondence and papers, 1987 (Box-folder 284: 1-2)
- History of Law in a Free Society Project, 1978 (Box-folder 284: 3)
- Center for Civic Education Board of Directors meetings, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 284: 4-5)
- Law-related education conference papers, 1981 (Box-folder 284: 6)
- Utilizing Federalist Principles in Civic Education Project correspondence and papers, 1982 -1985 (Box-folder 284: 7)
- Agency for Instructional Television correspondence and paper, 1981 (Box-folder 284: 8)
- Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution correspondence and newsletters, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 285: 1)
- National Bicentennial Competition on the Constitution and Bill of Rights correspondence, reports, and 1985-1990 (Box-folder 285: 2-9)
- Center for Civic Education newsletters, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 285: 10)
- Paul Hanna correspondence, papers, and proposals, 1980-1985 (Box-folder 286: 1-3)
- Hannna Collection Advisory Committee meetings, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 286: 4)
- Hoover Institution research proposals, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 286: 5-6)
- Hoover Institution annual report contributions, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 286: 7)
- Civic Education for the Third Century outlines and proposals, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 286: 8-9)
- Research materials, 1976-1989
  - National Institute of Education study of higher education, 1984 (Box-folder 287: 1)
  - Liberal arts, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 287: 2)
  - Educational reform, 1976-1989 (Box-folder 287: 3-6)
  - Twentieth Century Fund Task Force, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 287: 7)
  - Academic standards, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 287: 8)
  - Competency testing for teachers, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 287: 9)
  - Merit pay for teachers, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 287: 10)
  - College Board Project Equality, 1983 (Box-folder 287: 11)
  - Reforms of teacher education, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 288: 1)
  - Certification and accrediting of teachers, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 288: 2)
- Council of Learned Societies in Education meetings, 1982-1988 (Box-folder 288: 3)
- American Educational Research Association conferences, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 288: 4)
- American Educational Studies Association conferences, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 288: 5)
- Wendell W. Wright Education Building dedication, 1993 (Box-folder 288: 6)
- Jennings Randolph Forum meetings, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 289: 1-7)
- Council for the Advancement of Citizenship Board of Directors meetings, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 289: 8-9)
- Jennings Randolph Forum meetings, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 290: 1-2)
- Council for the Advancement of Citizenship materials, 1989-1992
  - General information, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 290: 3-5)
  - Membership meetings, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 290: 6)
  - Board of Directors meetings, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 290: 7-8)
  - Board of Directors meeting, 1991 (Box-folder 291: 1)
  - Bicentennial Leadership Project, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 291: 2-6)
  - Promotion of civic education, 1989 (Box-folder 291: 7)
  - United States Institute of Peace grant, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 291: 8)
  - Resource packets, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 292: 1)
  - Citizenship Education and Peace Project, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 292: 2)
- Jennings Randolph Forum meetings, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 292: 3-4)
- Articles on individual rights, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 292: 5)
- Clippings on the new federalism, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 292: 6)
- Freedoms Foundation publications, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 292: 7)
- American Bar Association meetings, 1927-1941 (Box-folder 292: 8)
- Jennings Randolph Forum meeting, 1991 (Box-folder 293: 1-2)
- Center for Civic Education Board of Directors meeting, 1991 (Box-folder 293: 3)
- Draft of statement for Senator Claiborne Pell, 1992 (Box-folder 293: 4)
- Articles on student violence and volunteerism, 1992 (Box-folder 293: 5)
- Center for Civic Education materials, 1909-1991
  - National Bicentennial Competition on the Constitution and Bill of Rights, 1991 (Box-folder 293: 6-7)
  - Board of Directors meetings, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 293: 8-9)
  - Board of Directors meetings, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 294: 1-6)
  - Board of Directors retreat, 1990 (Box-folder 294: 7)
- "A Personal Preface", 1991 (Box-folder 295: 1)
- "The Public Good", 1991 (Box-folder 295: 2)
- "The Nature of Politics and Government", 1990-1991 (Box-folder 295: 3)
- "Separation of Church and State", 1989-1991 (Box-folder 295: 4)
- "Human Rights", 1989-1991 (Box-folder 296: 1)
- "The Bill of Rights: Educating for Our Common Compact", 1991 (Box-folder 296: 2)
- "Historical Perspective", 1991 (Box-folder 296: 3)
- Civitas: A Framework for Civic Education, 1987-1991
  - Background materials, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 296: 3-4)
  - Drafts of texts, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 296: 5-6)
  - Research materials, 1987 (Box-folder 297: 1-9)
- "Teaching about the Constitution in American Schools", 1986
  - Draft, 1986 (Box-folder 298: 1)
  - Research materials, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 298: 2-6)
- National civics competition, 1992 (Box-folder 299: 1)
- Correspondence with Ralph Nader, 1992 (Box-folder 299: 2)
- Correspondence relating to the Center for Civic Education, 1989 (Box-folder 299: 3-4)
- In the First Person Singular: The Foundations of Education, 1992 (Box-folder 299: 5-7)
- "Education for Citizenship: Educational Goals and Curriculum Patterns", 1974 (Box-folder 299: 8)
- "Curriculum for the Educated Citizen", 1980 (Box-folder 299: 9)
- Research materials, 1940-1993
  - Religion and schools, 1946-1956 (Box-folder 300: 1)
  - Separation of church and state, 1949-1980 (Box-folder 300: 2-9)
  - Tax exemption for schools, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 301: 1)
  - Secular humanism, 1978-1985 (Box-folder 301: 2-3)
  - Religion and public life, 1982-1992 (Box-folder 301: 4)
  - Religious issues, 1947-1978 (Box-folder 301: 5-6)
  - Religion and education, 1976 (Box-folder 301: 7)
  - Demise of the Soviet Union, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 302: 1)
  - Persian Gulf War, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 302: 2)
  - Somalia and Islam, 1993 (Box-folder 302: 3)
  - Democratic revolution in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 302: 4-5)
  - Iran-Contra scandal, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 302: 6)
  - Global studies and education, 1976-1987 (Box-folder 303: 1-3)
  - Peace studies, 1989 (Box-folder 303: 4)
  - Human rights in the United States, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 303: 5)
  - Human rights in the United States, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 304: 1)
  - International human rights, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 304: 2-3)
  - Chinese student movement, 1989 (Box-folder 304: 4)
- Conference papers by others, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 304: 5-7)
  - "A Rationale for Stressing Law-Related Values in the Education of Citizens", 1982 (Box-folder 299: 10)
- Research materials, 1980-1991
  - 1980 political campaign (Box-folder 305: 1)
  - Conservatism and women, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 305: 2)
  - Reagan administration and civil rights, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 305: 3)
  - Iran-Contra scandal, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 305: 4)
  - Ronald Reagan and conservatism, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 305: 5)
  - Heritage Foundation, 1982 (Box-folder 306: 1)
  - 1988 political campaign (Box-folder 306: 1)
  - Bush administration and civil rights, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 306: 3)
  - Richard Viguerie and conservatism, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 306: 4)
- American Educational Studies Association newsletters, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 306: 5)
- Executive Summary of California Education publications and correspondence, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 306: 6)
- American Enterprise Institute correspondence and paper, 1982 (Box-folder 307: 1)
- Thomas Jefferson Research Center notes, 1983 (Box-folder 307: 2)
- Ethics and Public Policy Center newsletters, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 307: 4)
- American Bar Association correspondence and coference materials, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 307: 5-6)
- Foundation for Teaching Economics correspondence and conference paper, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 307: 7)
- History of Education Society newsletters and conference materials, 1988-1995 (Box-folder 307: 8)
- Far Western Philosophy of Education Society correspondence, 1986-1993 (Box-folder 307: 9)
- Society of Professors of Education, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 307: 10)
- Atlantic Council correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 307: 11)
- Paper on Prague conference on world standards in education, 1995 (Box-folder 307: 12)
- Pew Charitable Trusts proposals, 1987 (Box-folder 308: 1)
- "Janus-Faced Views of Educational Reform", 1988 (Box-folder 308: 2)
- Civitas National Review Council meetings, 1988 (Box-folder 308: 3)
- Civitas Framework Development Committee meetings, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 308: 4-10)
- Civitas Framework Development Committee meeting, 1989 (Box-folder 309: 1)
- Notes on human rights, 1990 (Box-folder 309: 2)
- Civitas: A Framework for Civic Education, 1989-1991
  - Correspondence and suggestions, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 309: 3-6)
  - Drafts, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 309: 7-9)
- "The Ultimate Goal of Civitas: Civic Virtue", 1990-1994
  - Drafts, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 310: 1-2)
  - Research materials, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 310: 3-6)
- "At Last - A Civic Lesson for All of Us", 1992 (Box-folder 310: 7)
- Civitas: A Framework for Civic Education, 1991-1992
- Civitas: A Framework for Civic Education, 1991-1992
  - Executive summary and press releases, 1991 (Box-folder 311: 1)
  - Promotion, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 311: 2-3)
  - Press notices and op-ed pieces, 1991 (Box-folder 311: 4)
- White House Conference on Character Building for a Democratic, Civil Society, 1998-1995 (Box-folder 311: 5)
- Pew Charitable Trusts Meeting on Civic Education, 1992 (Box-folder 312: 1)
- National Standards for Civics and Government project, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 312: 2-7)
- National Standards for Civics and Government project, 1994 (Box-folder 313: 1-6)
- "Antidote for Anti-Politics: A New Text of Civic Instruction", 1994 (Box-folder 313: 7)
- Civic Education for America's Third Century: Perspectives for the Public and the Teaching Profession, 1987-1994
  - Correspondence and research materials, 1987 (Box-folder 314: 1)
  - Flyer, 1988 (Box-folder 314: 2)
  - Contract, 1989 (Box-folder 314: 3)
  - Missing pages, 1988 (Box-folder 314: 3)
  - Promotion, 1988-1994 (Box-folder 314: 4-5)
- Reviews of The Civic Mission in Education Reform: Perspectives for the Public and Profession, 1989-1996 (Box-folder 314: 6)
- Mieklejohn Education Association materials, 1989-1994
  - Newsletters and correspondence, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 315: 1)
  - Report on experimental college, 1993 (Box-folder 315: 2)
  - Conference, 1990 (Box-folder 315: 3)
  - Reunions and convocations, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 315: 4-6)
- Correspondence with Bruce Fehn, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 315: 7)
- Correspondence with the University of Wisconsin Press, 1998 (Box-folder 315: 8)
- Excerpts from The College Charts Its Course, 1939 (Box-folder 316: 1)
- The University of Wisconsin: A History, 1925-1945 by E. David Cronon and John W. Jenkins, 1993-1995
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box-folder 316: 2)
  - Review, 1995 (Box-folder 316: 3)
  - Final draft, 1993 (Box-folder 316: 4)
- University of Wisconsin School of Education Alumni Achievement Award, 1993 (Box-folder 317: 1)
- Meiklejohn Education Association materials, 1995-1997
  - Convocations, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 317: 2-4)
  - Ad hoc committee, 1995 (Box-folder 317: 5)
- Civitas: A Framework for Civic Education, 1995-1996
  - Article, 1995 (Box-folder 318: 1-2)
  - Prague conference, 1995 (Box-folder 318: 1-3)
  - Robert H. Beck Colloquial Series lecture, University of Minnesota, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 318: 4-8)
- Correspondence, 1980-1997
  - General, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 319: 1)
  - Diane Ravich, 1990-1997 (Box-folder 319: 2)
  - Mary Futrell, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 319: 3)
  - Albert Shanker, 1991 (Box-folder 319: 4)
  - John Gardner, 1980-1997 (Box-folder 319: 5)
  - Hendrik Hertzberg, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 319: 6)
  - Leon Panetta, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 319: 7)
  - Sam Farr, 1993 (Box-folder 319: 8)
  - Wilton Dillon, 1993 (Box-folder 319: 9)
  - Bill Honig, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 319: 10)
  - Edward Meade, 1985 (Box-folder 319: 11)
  - Hodding Carter III, 1989 (Box-folder 319: 12)
  - Mario Cuomo, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 319: 13)
  - Marshall Smith, 1991 (Box-folder 319: 14)
  - Jim McClellan, 1994 (Box-folder 319: 15)
  - Diane Eisenberg, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 320: 1)
  - Diane Eisenberg, 1990-1996 (Box-folder 320: 1)
  - Nancy Warzer, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 320: 2)
  - Jane Coleman, 1993 (Box-folder 320: 3)
  - Kettering Foundation (Rob Lehman, David Matthew, Suzanne Morse), 1988-1989 (Box-folder 320: 4-5)
  - United States Information Agency (Pen Agnew), 1987 (Box-folder 320: 6)
  - Fiermantell and Sunburst Communications, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 320: 7)
  - Council for the Advancement of Citizenship, 1984-1991 (Box-folder 320: 8-9)
- "Jefferson and Civic Learning", 1994 (Box-folder 320: 10)
- "A Historic 'Jeffersonian Compact' on Education-But Where Was Jefferson?", 1989 (Box-folder 320: 11)
- Social Science Education Consortium conference, 1997 (Box-folder 320: 12)
- Correspondence, 1982-1997
  - Robert M. O'Neil, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 321: 1)
  - Teachers College, 1989-1997 (Box-folder 321: 2-3)
  - Larry Cremin, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 321: 4)
  - Linda Darling-Hammond, 1994 (Box-folder 321: 5)
  - Markie Hancock and Maxine Green, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 321: 6)
  - John A. Beineke, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 321: 7)
- "Teachers College and International Education, 1955-1975", 1991 (Box-folder 321: 8)
- Teachers for East Africa Program, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 321: 9)
- Visit of East African legislators to Stanford University, 1991 (Box-folder 321: 10)
- Proposal by John Fischer for Center for Civic Education, 1973 (Box-folder 321: 11)
- Indiana University honorary doctorate award, 1993 (Box-folder 322: 1)
- Indiana University National Board of Visitors meetings, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 322: 2)
- "The Great Task Remaining before Us", 1993
  - Background materials, 1993 (Box-folder 322: 3)
  - Drafts, 1993 (Box-folder 322: 4)
- California State University at Monterey Bay projects, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 322: 5-8)
- In the First Person Singular: The Foundations of Education, 1991-1997
  - Preface and introduction, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 323: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1997 (Box-folder 323: 2-3)
- Council of Learned Societies in Education meetings, 1987-1998 (Box-folder 323: 4)
- American Educational Studies Association history and correspondence, 1985-1998 (Box-folder 323: 5-6)
- "The Time Is Now: To Frame the Civic Formations of Teacher Education", 1993 (Box-folder 323: 7)
- Correspondence with E.K. Fretwell, Jr., 1985-1998 (Box-folder 324: 1)
- Letters to the editor, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 324: 2)
- "Charter Schools: Make Sure They Meet National Standards", 1998 (Box-folder 324: 3)
- "Bill of Rights", 1991 (Box-folder 324: 4)
- Correspondence with Charles Bahmueller, 1996 (Box-folder 324: 5)
- "Education for Civitas: The Lessons Americans Must Learn", 1997 (Box-folder 324: 6)
- Distribution and mailing lists, 1985-1997 (Box-folder 324: 7-8)
- "Civic Education and Human Rights", 1989 (Box-folder 325: 1)
- Hoover Institution Conference on National Service, 1989 (Box-folder 325: 2)
- "The Pledge of Allegiance: A Case for Studying the Constitution in Civic Education", 1989 (Box-folder 325: 3)
- Monterery Lyceum seminars, 1989 (Box-folder 325: 4-5)
- Review of book by Richard Pratte, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 325: 6)
- Review of book by Charles C. Moskos, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 325: 7)
- American Federation of Teachers statement, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 325: 8-9)
- Civitas International exchange programs, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 326: 1-3)
- Center for Civic Education Board of Directors meetings, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 326: 4-11)
- Correspondence on education in Australia, 1988-1996 (Box-folder 327: 1)
- "Analysis of Civic Education in the United States: National Standards and Civic Education in the U.S.", 1991 (Box-folder 327: 2-3)
- "Historical Perspective on the Civic role of the School in American Society", 1985 (Box-folder 327: 4)
- Correspondence with C.T. Hu, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 327: 5)
- Correspondence with Judith Torney-Purta, 1995 (Box-folder 327: 6)
- Civitas Panamericano conference, 1996 (Box-folder 327: 7)
- Education Commission of the States symposium, 1985 (Box-folder 327: 8-9)
- Correspondence with Anne Lewis, 1988 (Box-folder 327: 10)
- William F. Russell professorship appointment, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 328: 1-2)
- "Reflections on Forty Years in the Foundations Department at Teachers College", 1975 (Box-folder 328: 3)
- William Heard Kilpatrick Award, 1975 (Box-folder 328: 4)
- Festschrift, 1993 (Box-folder 328: 5)
- American Civil Liberties Union Academic Freedom Committee meetings, 1950-1956 (Box-folder 328: 6)
- Columbia University Academic Freedom Project, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 328: 7)
- The American Tradition in Religion and Education correspondence, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 328: 8)
- Notes on segregation, 1973-1990 (Box-folder 328: 9)
- Reviews of The Revival of Civic Learning, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 328: 10)
- The Morality of Democratic Citizenship correpsondence, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 328: 11)
- Biographical clippings, 1926-1927 (Box-folder 329: 1)
- "The Liberal Arts and Professional Education in the Preparation of Teachers: An International Perspective", 1959 (Box-folder 329: 2)
- "What Kind of Pedagogy?: Not 'Soft,' Not 'Hard," but 'Firm' ", 1959 (Box-folder 329: 3)
- "A Liberal Education and the Prescribed Curriculum in the American College", 1937 (Box-folder 329: 4)
- Clippings and program relating to speech to Parents Association, 1939 (Box-folder 329: 5)
- Clipping with views on teachers, 1948 (Box-folder 329: 6)
- "Freedom and Responsibility in American Education", 1952 (Box-folder 329: 7)
- "Our Responsibility for Freedom in Education", 1953 (Box-folder 329: 8)
- "The Profession in Periods of Tension", 1953 (Box-folder 329: 9)
- "The Relation between Religion and Education", 1956 (Box-folder 329: 10)
- Review of book by Arthur Bestor, 1984 (Box-folder 329: 11)
- "Education" (Box-folder 329: 12)
- "States Rights and Education", 1957 (Box-folder 329: 13)
- "James Madison: The Bill of Rights and Education", 1958 (Box-folder 329: 14)
- Maryland survey of education, 1959 (Box-folder 329: 15)
- "Public Funds for Parochial Schools? No!", 1960 (Box-folder 329: 16)
- "Scholarship and Education in a Free Society", 1960 (Box-folder 329: 17)
- "Search for Freedom-The Story of American Education", 1960 (Box-folder 329: 18)
- Letter to the editor in support of John F. Kennedy, 1960 (Box-folder 329: 19)
- "Tension in Teacher Education", 1960 (Box-folder 329: 20)
- Review of book by Max Rafferty, 1964 (Box-folder 329: 21)
- Article on education for Encyclopedia Britannica, 1971 (Box-folder 329: 22)
- "Charting Our Position on the Way to...", 1969 (Box-folder 329: 23)
- "America's Role in International Education: A Perspective on Thirty Years", 1969 (Box-folder 329: 24)
- "International Education: Overview", 1971 (Box-folder 329: 25)
- "Arnold J. Toynbee's Philosophy of History", 1952-1953 (Box-folder 329: 26)
- "The Public School: Assaults on a Great Idea", 1973 (Box-folder 330: 1)
- "The Uncompleted Dream: the Public School as a Great Idea", 1973 (Box-folder 330: 2)
- "Outstanding Foundations Books of 1973", 1974 (Box-folder 330: 3)
- "Public Education and the Public Faith", 1974 (Box-folder 330: 4)
- "Public Education and Political Community", 1974 (Box-folder 330: 5-6)
- "Foundations of Education and the New Civism", 1975 (Box-folder 330: 7)
- Critiques, 1976-1986 (Box-folder 330: 8)
- "The Search for Purpose in American Education", 1975-1976 (Box-folder 330: 9)
- "Historical Perspective on Civic Education in the United States", 1976 (Box-folder 330: 10)
- "Citizen Education Historical Analysis: Final Report", 1978 (Box-folder 331: 1-4)
- "Once Again the Question for Liberal Public Educators: Whose Twilight?", 1976 (Box-folder 331: 5)
- "The Search for Equality," chapter 11 of Public Education in the United States, 1978 (Box-folder 331: 6)
- "Public Education in a Pluralistic Society", 1977 (Box-folder 331: 7)
- "The Public School and Moral Authority", 1977 (Box-folder 331: 8)
- "Education for Citizenship: The Oldest, Newest Innovation in the Schools", 1977 (Box-folder 331: 9)
- "The Revival of Civic Learning: A Rationale for the Education of Citizens", 1979 (Box-folder 332: 1)
- National Council for the Social Studies guidelines, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 332: 2)
- "Educational Vouchers: The Private Pursuit of the Public Purse", 1979 (Box-folder 332: 3)
- "Should California Adopt School Vouchers? No: Public Schools Are the Foundation of Our Democracy", 1979 (Box-folder 332: 4)
- "Curriculum for the Educated Citizen", 1980 (Box-folder 332: 5)
- Foreward to Daring to Dream, 1980 (Box-folder 332: 6)